British Caribbean Documents
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
British Caribbean Documents
1664-1857
1765-1825
GEN MSS 1412
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.54
A collection of manuscript deeds, wills, leases, letters, and other legal and financial documents concerning eighteenth- and nineteenth-century estates and plantations on islands in the British West Indies.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown. Possibly formerly owned by James Coleman, genealogical and antiquarian manuscripts vendor, London.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by island and chronologically thereunder.
Custodial History
Most of the manuscripts are listed in Volumes II and III of Vere Langford Oliver's six-volume compendium Caribbeana, being Miscellaneous Papers Related to the History, Genealogy, Topography, and Antiquities of the British West Indies (London: Mitchell Hughes and Clarke, 1910-1919). Footnotes in those volumes associate the documents with James Coleman, a dealer who specialized in genealogical and antiquarian manuscripts active in London and Tottenham from 1862 to 1905; most of the documents have printed descriptions clipped from a sales catalogue attached to their versos.
Scope and Contents
A collection of manuscript deeds, wills, leases, letters, and other legal and financial documents concerning eighteenth- and nineteenth-century estates and plantations on fourteen islands in the British West Indies: Antigua, Barbados, Dominica, Grenada, Carriacou, Haiti, Jamaica, Nevis, New Providence, Saint Christopher (Saint Kitts), Saint Vincent, Tobago, Tortola, and Trinidad. Prominent among the landowners represented in the collection are Clotworthy Upton, Lord Templetown, who owned estates on Grenada, and Christopher Bethell Codrington of, who owned Clare Hall on Antigua. Several of the documents in the collection include references to, or contain schedules of, slaves on the estates. Most of the manuscripts are listed in Volumes II and III of Caribbeana, edited by Vere Langford Oliver, and have printed descriptions clipped from a sales catalogue attached to their versos.
Administration of estates -- West Indies; Plantation owners -- West Indies; Slaveholders -- West Indies; Slavery -- West Indies; Antigua -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Barbados -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Carriacou Island (Grenada) -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Dominica -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Great Britain -- Colonies -- Administration; Grenada -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Haiti -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Jamaica -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Nevis -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; New Providence Island (Bahamas) -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Saint Kitts and Nevis -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Saint Vincent -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Tobago (Trinidad and Tobago) -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Tortola (British Virgin Islands) -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Trinidad -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Deeds -- West Indies -- 18th century; Financial records -- West Indies -- 18th century; Financial records -- West Indies -- 19th century; Parchment (animal material) -- England -- 18th century; Angerstein, John Julius, 1735-1823; Codrington, Christopher Bethell, 1764-1843; Gambier, James, 1772-1844; Hankey, Thomson, 1773-1855; Mason, John Thomson, 1765-1824; Picton, Thomas, Sir, 1758-1815; Upton, Clotworthy, Baron Templetown, 1721-1785; Coleman, James, active 1862-1887 -- Ownership
- Antigua
  - Royal decree by George III concerning income from Antigua, 1818 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    With royal seal.
  - Schedule of the 322 slaves at Clare Hall plantation owned by Christopher Bethell Codrington, 1828 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 53)
- Barbados
  - Deed between William Green, of London, and Nicholas Wilcox, of the Island of Barbados, 1731-11-15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Seal of William Green.
  - Deed between Benjamin Duce, of St. Niclastice, Barbados, and John Fridenburg, of the City of London, 1767-11-12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Seals of Benjamin Duce, and Thomas and Ann Davies.
  - Letters Patent to Thomas Carter by George III to be Provost Marshall General of Barbados, 1801-08-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Signed by William Pollock; with royal seal.
  - Original will of Henry Bishop, of the island of Barbados, 1803-07-29 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 60)
  - The Administration with the will of Valentine Clark, of St. Michael, Barbardos, 1803-12-17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Power of Attorney from William Ewart, William C. Rutson, Archibald Maxwell, et al. to William Barton, of Liverpool to obtain possession of estates on Barbados, 1807-02-03 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Engraved document with manuscript insert and several seals, including mayoral seal of Liverpool; signed by mayor Thomas Molyneux.
  - Administration, with will, of goods and chattles of John Bedford, Judge of the Vice-Admiralty Court of Barbados, 1808-07-08 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Dominica
  - Deed between Garrett Burton, of Rosare, and John Woodville, of the City of London, 1768-09-29 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 54)
    About "Woodford Hill," an estate in St. Andrew parish, Dominica; seal of Garrett Burton.
  - Original grant by George III, with plan, for certain lands on Dominica to James Laing, Robert Reid, and John Lucas, 1804-07-28 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 61)
  - Copy of the will and codicil of John Gillon, late of Dominica, 1809-12-13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Deed between John and Mary Laidlaw, of Dominica, and John Bruce and Dugald Laidlaw, 1823-07-09 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Seals of John and Mary Laidlaw.
- Grenada
  - Deed between John His of Hamburg, and Peter Texier of London, 1765-06-06 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Seals of John His and Pierre Texier.
  - Notarized statement certifying Peter Texier's arrival in St. George in August 1765, 1765-09-06 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Seal of Alexander Lymson.
  - Three deeds between John Cross, Robert Bogle, and John Baird, all of Glasgow, and Charlton Palmer, and James Oswald, of London, 1766-05-20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Seals of John Cross, Robert Bogle, and John Baird.
  - Copy of deed between Joseph Disilles and his wife Margaret E. Cavalier Thain, and Alexandra Wilson, 1767-05-19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Regarding the sale of the David plantation, including land, buildings, slaves, and livestock.
  - Deed between John Cross, Robert Bogle, and John Baird, all of Glasgow, and Charlton Palmer, and James Oswald, of London, 1768-09-03 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    About plantation on Grenada; seals of John Cross, Robert Bogle, and John Baird, including seals of mayors of Glasgow and London.
  - Bond between James Tourneissen, of Switzerland, and Anthony Colombies, of London, 1771-01-04 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    About lands and plantations in Grenada; seals of both parties.
  - Probate of the will of Pontius Pintard, of the town of St. George, 1774-10-24 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Deed between John Porteus, Deputy Provost Marshall of Grenada, and Alexander Wilson for the sale of Mount Alexander estate, 1775-10-20 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 55)
    Seal of John Porteus.
  - Copy of deed between Andrew Irwin, James Campbell and George Leonard Haunton, and Roume de Saint Laurent and William Donaldson, 1776-07-17 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 56)
  - Deed between Sir Alexander Crawfurd, James Hay, Samuel Wood, and William Wise to William Junor, release of Grenville Vale estate, 1789-04-09 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 57)
    Seals of Hay, Wood, and Wise.
  - Deed between William Wise, of St. George, and William Junor, of St. Patrick, 1789-04-28 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 58)
    Seal of William Wise.
  - Accounts of estates under the management of Robert Orme, 1795-1799, 1799-02-28 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fair copy of two letters from Thomson Hankey of London, to Richard Mauly of Grenada, 1807-07 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Regarding production of sugar and movement of slaves on the plantations.
  - Sketch of Lord Templetown's Account, prepared by Thomson Hankey, 1817-05-27 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    "Mr. Hankey's statement of the Grenada property."
  - Account of the extent and history of the Grande Bras, St. Cloud, and Chantilly estates in the parish of St. Andrew, 1819-03 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    An historical account starts with the deaths of Peter Simond (1785) and John Hankey (1792), with a description and accounting of slaves, pounds of sugar, and gallons of rum produced 1800-1818; includes an "Abstract from the Register of Slaves"; signed by James McNure. Accompanied by a letter from [Thomas?] Bridgewater to William Wilkinson of London, dated March 15, 1819.
  - Note of the late Lord Templetown's account in Thomson Hankey's hand, 1820-04-20 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Accounts of Grande Bras estate current to the 30th April 1820, signed by Thomson Hankey, 1820-04-30 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Lease indenture between William Johnstone, late of Grenada now Paris, and John Ross, late of Grenada now of Aberdeen, 1825-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Relating to the coffee plantation Granton, formerly known as Colebrook,, in the parish of St. George. Appended is a schedule of the estate's 119 slaves listing each name, age, colour, country of origin, and conspicuous marks or physical condition.
  - Lease between Samuel Amy Severne, of Northampton County, and George Edward Anson of London, 1839-04-12 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    For the estate New Hampshire in the parish of St. George.
  - Deed between Samuel Amy Severne, Catherine Julia Stuart, Maria Elizabeth Stuart, Catherine Juliana Stuart, Charles Ford, and George Edward Anson, 1839-04-13 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    About estates in the parish of St. George. Seals of Samuel A. Severne, Catherine Julia Stuart, Catherine Juliana Stuart, Maria Elizabeth Stuart, Charles Ford, and George Edward Anson.
  - Accounts of Grand Bras, St. Cloud Chantilly estates, current to 30th April 1839, prepared by Thomson Hankey, 1839-04-30 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Accounts of Grand Bras, St. Cloud Chantilly estates, current to the 30th April 1842, prepared by Thomson Hankey, 1842-04-30 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Abstract of the title of Anthony Percy Upton, Mary Howard, James Singleton, and Sophia Upton to their share of the Grand Bras Estate under the will of Lord Templetown, and agreed to be sold to Thomson Hankey, 1857-09-22 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 62)
  - Carriacou
    - Indenture between John Reid of Carriacou, and Jacob Van-Wylick and James Ballmer of the City of London, 1772-11-16 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 59)
      Regarding Bellair, a cotton plantation; seals of all parties.
- Haiti
  - Administration of the goods unadministered of Alexander Cranfurd, of Mole-Saint-Nicolas, 1800-05-13 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Probate of the will of John Pillon, formerly of St. Domingo then City of Orleans, 1855-08-17 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Jamaica
  - Six letters and notes relating to the Booth, Barrett, Mason, and Pye families, who had estates in Jamaica, 1747-1800 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Letters from Edward Booth to John Holliday, John Thomson Mason to Charles Pye, and Charles Pye to John Thomson Mason, regarding Booth family wills and estates.
  - Appellants case between Henry Thomas Broughton and Phillis Roper Broughton, and Elizabeth Jackson and others, the creditors of Charles Kelsall, Esq., circa 1800 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 63)
    Report of a law case which recites deed of 1776 between Charles Kelsall and Rebecca his wife of the 1st part and George Clarke, Esq., and Susannah his wife, daughter of Charles Kelsall, by which one third was settled on the Clarkes; Thomas Stephen and Rose Fuller, of the City of London, are mentioned largely in this case, and the plantations are in the parish of St. Mary in Jamaica. Report printed in London by Sabine and Son of, Shoe Lane.
  - Accounts of Samuel Hilton concerning Bounty Hall Sugar Plantation covering 1827-1830, 1830-06 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 64)
- Nevis
  - Lease between Anne, David, and Richard Gardner, all of Nevis, and Alexandra Houston, John Clerk, William Crichton, William McDowall, all of City of London, 1769 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    For a plantation, Rawlins's Land, in the parish of St. James; lists names of slaves included with the property. Seals of Anne and David Gardner.
  - Deed between Patrick O'Flaherty, late of Nevis now Westminster (London), and Rev. Richard Neate of Holborn, of Middx., and Archibald Thomson, of Nevis, 1769 October 28 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Seals of O'Flaherty and Thomson.
- New Providence
  - Probate of the will of Robert Rumer, of New Providence, 1828 April 12 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Saint Christopher (Saint Kitts)
  - Articles of agreement and letter of attorney between Henry Slingsby, of London, and Henry Brouncker, of St. Christopher, appointing the former as collector of the parts of Old Road and Sandy Point, 1736 December 10 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Seals of both parties on agreement. Seal of Slingsby on Letter of Attorney.
  - Deed between Lord James, Lady Sophia, and William Cranstoun and John Banister, James Hammond, and William Manning, of London, about grant and demise of lands and slaves for 99 years, 1770 June 21 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Seals of James, Sophia, and William Cranstoun.
  - Marriage settlement between Charles Philips and Elizabeth Spence, 1772 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Seals of Charles Palmer, James Spence, and Charlton Palmer.
  - Two deeds between Charles Philips, late of St. Christopher, and William Smith, Ingam Foster, and Charlton Palmer, 1777 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Seals of Philips and Palmer. Includes inventory of slaves and cattle.
  - Deed between Charles Philips, late of St. Christopher, and William Smith, Ingam Foster, and Charlton Palmer about plantations and lands in the Parish of Trinity, Palmeto Point, 1777 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Seal of Charles Philips. The lands mentioned formerly belonged to Sir John Boye.
  - Letter of Appointment of Joseph Paice as trustee of lands under the will of Thomas Lucas, deceased, with the consent of John J. and Elizabeth Angerstein, John Beach, and William Withers, 1789 March 11 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Seals of Joseph Paice, John Beach, John J. and Elizabeth Angerstein
  - Lease between Elizabeth Angerstein, Joseph Paice, and John Beach and William Withers, all of London, 1789 March 12 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Seals of Angerstein, Paice, and Beach.
  - Release of plantations of the late Thomas Lucas to John J. and Elizabeth Angerstein, Joseph Paice, John Beach, and William Withers and Oliver Cromwell, all of London, 1789 March 13 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Seals of J. and E. Angerstein, Paice, Beach, and Cromwell.
  - Deed between William Temple Pole, Scrope Berdmore, Andrew Berkeley Drummond, George Templer, Owen Putland Meyrick, and William Lowndes Stone, for several plantations and lands in several parishes, 1807 June 23 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Seals of all parties.
- Saint Vincent
  - Letter of attorney between Michael White and John Suvanion regarding the sugar plantation Chateau Bellair, 1788-05-01 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Seal of Michael White.
- Tobago
  - Deed between the devisees of John Walker and John Anderson et al., 1804-05-05 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Conveyance of the Providence Plantation on Tobago to a term of 1,000 years. Indenture of fifteen parchment sheets; fourteen seals of all parties.
    Parties include Joanna Thomson, Andrew Hunter, Thomas Davidson (formerly Thomas Randall) of Edinburgh; James, Margaret, and Jane Walker of Edinburgh; John Anderson of Tobago; Christopher William Irvine of Bath; and many others.
  - Deed between John and Janet Learmont, of Dumfries, and John Learmont Jr. to sell slaves and land, 1820-12-22 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Contains a schedule of slaves with name, age, colour, country, and "usual employment," with seals of John and Janet Learmont.
- Tortola
  - Two deeds between Payne Georges, William Manning, and John Proctor Anderson, all of London, 1813-12-18 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    Two deeds in one document; seals of Payne Georges.
- Trinidad
  - Official copy of letters patent issued by George III to Thomas Picton to be Governor and Commander-in-Chief of Trinidad, 1801-05-29 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Deed between David Park and Robert Orr, both of Trinidad, and William Lushington of the City of London, 1817-10-06 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    Seal of David Park.
- Other Documents
  - Deed between Mary Jorden, of Alnwicke, widow of Robert Jorden, late of Hullbrook, Thomas Jorden, of Wittney, and Richard Jorden, of Hullbrook and William Jorden, of the city of London, 1664-12-19 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Deed of distribution of the estate of John Taylor, Bristol, 1726-06-01 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    Multiple signatures and seals.
  - Offical copy of letters patent issued by by George III to Sir James Gambier to be Consul-General in the Portuguese Dominions in South America, 1803-05-02 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    Royal Seal.
  - Letter of Attorney by Stanley Bullock, of Rolls Bridge, and Robert Bullock, of Madras in the East Indies, to Robert Langley Appleyard, 1825 December 20 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 65)
    Seals of Stanley and Robert Bullock.
  - Receipt [for Robert Langley Appleyard], 1826-08 (Box 5, Folder 52)